[SPEAKER_00]: Flat country.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can put something on about your trip to Notre Dame this morning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, let's talk about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I went to Notre Dame today, this morning.
[SPEAKER_00]: We got there about 10.30 after a leisurely breakfast, packing the car.
[SPEAKER_00]: Left the Capital Motel, which was just off the interstate north of South Bend.
[SPEAKER_00]: and we parked and came down into the campus park near the football stadium in a student parking lot and went over to the library.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wanted to see Francis Clark, who's the head of the microfilming division of Notre Dame Libraries, from whom I've purchased the sporting life.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wanted to ask if he had the rest of my sporting life ready, and I also just wanted to find out what kind of an operation he ran there.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was unclear on it, what the sports had to do with it all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Was this a Notre Dame operation or a private operation?
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm still not sure about that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He met us in the elevators and took us down to their maze of underground hallways and corridors.
[SPEAKER_00]: They call it a maze, and it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: He took us into his office.
[SPEAKER_00]: Guy about 5'10", chubby, funny looking, black hair, probably around 40.
[SPEAKER_00]: Very pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was kind of a little distant at first, but as we got going he warmed up and was laughing jovially at the end there.
[SPEAKER_00]: He took us into his office and
[SPEAKER_00]: sat us down there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was kind of a messy place with piles of newspapers and magazines and stacks of miscellaneous documents all over the place.
[SPEAKER_00]: His desk was cluttered, looked like Harold Dean's.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then he started talking a little bit about what he was doing, then I wanted to start from the beginning, so he told us about the operation there, how they
[SPEAKER_00]: do this baseball microfilming.
[SPEAKER_00]: He does it largely on his own.
[SPEAKER_00]: He does it with the library funds which are available and other things that are not, that are just funny left over.
[SPEAKER_00]: He gets this material from various other libraries, copies it very painstakingly and returns it to the other library.
[SPEAKER_00]: In some cases, sometimes they just throw it away.
[SPEAKER_00]: He copied the Columbus Crisis, five years of that, and then he was allowed to keep the originals, which he says he hasn't sold.
[SPEAKER_00]: Must be a beautiful edition of rag paper.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bill Loffman of Chicago, the airline's pilot, who got me onto this guy, Clark.
[SPEAKER_00]: He brings a lot of stuff in in his station wagon and a U-Haul it.
[SPEAKER_00]: and Clark photographs and films it, then Loffman carries the stuff off again.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's brought him a lot of the Cleveland Plain dealers, most of those.
[SPEAKER_00]: How many stacks of those did he bring down there?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It took a whole U-Haul it, and his station wagon filled up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And about, from the wall to the ceiling, about five feet out,
[SPEAKER_00]: 10 feet long.
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems like a lot of things he does, he has to do it without their knowing about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like one day, on a Sunday afternoon, his boss came in when he was wheeling in a pile of those clay dooders, I guess, and he had to say he was cleaning things out or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: He keeps those shelves in his office filled with stuff so if there's something comes in that he wants to do, then he'd take one off and replace it, throw out the other one, what's already there, because they've all been photographed.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's pretty tricky.
[SPEAKER_00]: He took us in, showed us his drawers of master negatives for the microfilm copies they have, all their baseball stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: The old occasional New York sporting papers of the 60s, 70s, 80s, and 90s.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Sporting Life from 83 right down to 1917.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Sporting News only from 1918 on with a number of big gaps in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He wants to borrow some of mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: 30s and 40s help fill up a gap he has there.
[SPEAKER_00]: They must have the world's greatest collection of Catholic papers on microfilm from all over the place.
[SPEAKER_00]: He wanted to sell us some of those, I think.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, they have every one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ever printed in Ohio?
[SPEAKER_01]: Kentucky?
[SPEAKER_00]: Missouri, certainly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Missouri.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some of Kansas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kansas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Michigan.
[SPEAKER_01]: And a couple others.
[SPEAKER_01]: They must be working on that though because they didn't have all the states done.
[SPEAKER_01]: And over a thousand parish histories.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I think it's five or a thousand or so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, and then he's got a thousand at home or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there have been over 17,000 printed so this is a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: A parish meeting, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Church history, small church, the Boas denomination.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a pretty good history zone, the one he showed me.
[SPEAKER_00]: The picture looked like a college yearbook.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was a capsule history of Notre Dame.
[SPEAKER_00]: These master negatives
[SPEAKER_00]: are available for private purchase or for institutional purchase.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they're all beautifully boxed.
[SPEAKER_00]: They run around $12 a roll.
[SPEAKER_00]: He had the thing I'm going to get, which I didn't know about, two rolls of scrapbooks from the Charles Mears collection in the Cleveland Public Library.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lockman, I guess, brought those over, or somebody did.
[SPEAKER_00]: Probably Lockman.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stacks and stacks of scrapbooks.
[SPEAKER_00]: A couple thousand pages, he thinks, of scrapbooks.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they're on about a roll and a half, and I'm gonna buy that from him.
[SPEAKER_00]: My sporting life, by the way, which I have ordered and bought,
[SPEAKER_00]: It was shipped out Friday, he told us.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he'd known we were coming, he would have hung on to it, but it should be home when I get there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Took us back into the filming room where they film the papers and guides, books or magazines, whatever they're filming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Showed me a batch of old baseball guides from the nearest collection.
[SPEAKER_00]: five boxes of those, he brought out one box and showed me which had, among other things, a bound edition of the 19-2, 3, and 4th reach guides.
[SPEAKER_00]: All bound together beautifully in leather.
[SPEAKER_00]: Three guides in beautiful shape.
[SPEAKER_00]: And some things I'd never seen before, the early Hoosu and baseball guns, the originals, 1916, 18, 1920, some of those with Babe Ruth on the cover.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've never seen those.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are those available in reprints?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you can get them in reprints, but I've never seen the originals on sale anywhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: Paul Frizz bought a 1922 up in Detroit and he sold me that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those, uh... And is this the Cleveland Public Library that it is?
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't get into it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Semenuk was telling me this, you have to.
[SPEAKER_00]: They've got a catalog.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although, this guy said they didn't know what they had, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's what he said.
[SPEAKER_00]: But Semenuk says they had a catalog, and you just have to go in the room there and check through their list and sign a slip for what you want and then go get it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, now, how can they be so careful of it when goodness knows how long he's had those five boxes?
[SPEAKER_01]: there and he's not in any hurry to microfilm them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is he?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's valuable stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe they don't know the value.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, does this make you wonder?
[SPEAKER_00]: Loftman and Clark met in St. Louis in a secondhand bookstore.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's, uh, I don't know what they're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Clark was working in St. Louis there and doing some things.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said a lot about Johnson Spink, too.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says Johnson Spink has a little interest in baseball or helping researchers in his own industry, though.
[SPEAKER_00]: in the dollar.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're never going to get much help from him on anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he was there in St. Louis copying something and he ran into Loffman in the bookstore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Loffman was flying in and out of St. Louis then and they just, they frequented this bookstore and they got to know each other and out of this developed the weather.
[SPEAKER_00]: Clark was at Notre Dame then.
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess he wasn't there but maybe when he came to Notre Dame
[SPEAKER_00]: and became in charge of this microfilming division.
[SPEAKER_00]: He may have contacted Loffman about the possibility of re-filming all of this stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: So they worked very close for many years on this.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're now between exits 10 and 11, aren't we?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now about 2 to 35.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're going to be turning off at Angola and going north to the cold water and the Battle Creek area and try to introduce some ballplayers.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tonight or tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pick up Kathy tomorrow night or Thursday morning at home.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything else before we sign off?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, let's sign off right now and then maybe we'll think of something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Signing off.